A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Program Area One FA572
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Program Area One
1953-1970, bulk 1962-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fox, Melvin J. (1913-2003)
Passin, Herbert
Ford Foundation
FA572
2.28 Cubic Feet 6 Hollinger boxes
The collection was created by combining inactive records from various staff members within the International Division. The records span various decades from 1953 to 1970. The collection consists of Field Office Files and portions of the subject files of two Foundation staff members, Herbert Passin and Melvin Fox. The Field Office files hold correspondence, memoranda and reports originating from the Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) and South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) regional offices. Melvin Fox's subject files primarily pertain to the Language Development Study (1966-1967). Herbert Passin's subject files document his work as a consultant, focusing on education and cooperation between the United States and Japan, including basic dockets on the Foundation's Japan program (1963-1966) and support for English as a Second Language (1966).
Biographical / Historical
Melvin J. Fox was born on November 26, 1913 and graduated from American University in 1940 with a B.A. in International Economics. He joined the Ford Foundation in July 1951 as a consultant on international affairs and served as part of its charter staff. In November of the same year he became a staff associate and, in 1953, he advanced to Executive Associate for International Training and Research (ITR). Mr. Fox was promoted to Program Associate in October of 1957 and he served as Associate Director of the International Training and Research Program from 1961 through 1966. In early 1967, he became Program Officer for Planning and Evaluation in the International Division, and later that year was promoted to Deputy Representative for West Africa within the Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program. Mr. Fox subsequently held the positions of Program Officer for the Middle East and Africa (1970) and Program Advisor for MEA (1972) before rising to Representative for West Africa in May 1975. From September 5 to November 2, 1983, he became Acting Representative for the Developing Countries Program in Lagos, Nigeria. During his time at Ford, his work focused on foreign academic exchange, the teaching of the English language abroad, development projects in Africa, and African studies at U.S. Universities. Mr. Fox died in 1998.
Herbert Passin was born in Chicago on December 16, 1916 and graduated from the University of Illinois with a B.A. in Genetics. Later, in 1941, he received a B.A. and a M.A. in Anthropology from Northwestern University.
When World War II broke out, Mr. Passin learned Japanese at an army language school, and in December 1945, served as chief of the Public Opinion and Sociological Research Division in General MacArthur's headquarters in Tokyo. He later held positions at the University of California, the Social Science Research Council in Japan, Ohio State University, the Congress of Cultural Freedom, the University of Washington in Seattle, and Columbia University in New York.
The Ford Foundation hired Mr. Passin as a consultant for his expertise on Japan in 1962. He served as a program advisor during the Foundation's expansion into Japan. In 1967, Mr. Passin helped found the Shimoda Conference and the first U.S.-Japan parliamentary exchange program. He returned to Columbia University, where he chaired the Sociology Department from 1973 to 1977. He died on February 26, 2003 at the age of 86.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 3 series.
Scope and Contents
The International Division Program Area One Files are an artificially created collection of records from the International Division (ID) and International Training and Research (ITR) spanning from 1953 to 1970. The collection consists of Field Office Files and portions of the subject files of two staff members, Herbert Passin and Melvin Fox.
The Field Office Files contain correspondence, memoranda and reports originating from the Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) and South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) regional offices. The correspondence in the field office files relates to then-ongoing programs, such as the Foundation's support for the distribution of inter-uterine devices for birth control in India (1965-1966). Internal memoranda describe policy issues, from cost of living expenses for Foundation staff and local litigation over housing in Pakistan to Foundation policy on travel and study awards. Reports include one on a Foundation mission to Mexico (1964) and an economic and development report on India (1964). The subject files of Melvin Fox contained in this collection primarily pertain to a Language Development Study (1966-1967). The study researched the best method for teaching languages, particularly foreign or second languages. The correspondence associated with the study reveals some of the academic disputes over the findings.
Herbert Passin, an expert on Japan who served as a program advisor for the Foundation's expansion into Asia, is one of the few consultants whose files have been retained. His subject files focus on education and cooperation between the United States and Japan, including basic dockets on the Foundation's Japan program (1963-1966) and support for English as a Second Language (1966).
Related Materials
F548 Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files, 1956-1990. This collection documents various periods of the Foundation's overseas programs between 1956 and 1990. It includes additional office files of Melvin Fox.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation has been engaged in overseas work since the early 1950s. The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the future. In 1951, the Foundation established two of its first grant programs, Overseas Development (OD) and Overseas Training and Research (OTR). The granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. South and Southeast Asia were the initial focus, with India and Pakistan receiving the majority of grants. A more limited number of grants were issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants also was initiated for the Near East. In 1957, Overseas Development further expanded to include programs in Latin America.
In 1957, the Foundation established a program in International Training and Research (ITR) the goal of which was to strengthen American competence in foreign affairs and international relations. ITR supported scholarship and teaching in areas where American knowledge and trained personnel were limited. The Foundation offered area studies in Asia, Africa, the Near East, the Soviet Union, and East Europe. In its international training and exchange programs, the Foundation and its grantees coordinated closely with the U.S. State Department, which sponsored exchanges between the United States and other countries as a matter of government policy.
During the first couple decades of the Foundation's existence the differentiation between program areas had yet to be established. According to the 1949 Gaithner Report that laid the groundwork for the Ford Foundation's work as an international philanthropy, the goal of Program Area One was the Establishment of Peace. This program had four parts: the mitigation of world tensions, the development of the understanding and conditions for peace among peoples of the world, the strengthening of the United Nations, and the improvement of both private and public American participation in world affairs. Much of the work of the Overseas Development Program therefore fell under the auspices of Program Area One.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international programs such as International Training and Research (ITR) and Population, became part of a single International Division (ID). A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). DCP was again restructured in 1989, resulting in the separating of programs in Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA) as independent program areas.
- Field Office Files, 1957-1970; I; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, memoranda and reports from the Foundation's overseas field offices in Latin America and the Caribbean and South and Southeast Asia. The Foundation's operations in India are particularly well documented.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Census -- 1970 Round of National Censuses -- Memoranda, Background, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - English as a Second Language (ESL) Final Report, 1964 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation -- Grants in Overseas Agriculture -- Report, Memoranda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation -- Policy Issues -- Reports on Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation -- "Responsibility for International Activities" Memorandum, 1957 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fox, Melvin -- Ford Foundation Foreign or Second Language Activities, 1951-1966, 1967 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Bell, Wilheim -- Trip Schedule and Background, 1967 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Caribbean Program -- Self Study, 1966 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Cost of Living Tables, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Ford Foundation Mission to Mexico Report, 1964 November-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Housing Allowances -- Memoranda, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Travel and Study Manual, circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manitzas, Nita -- Proposed Grant Information, Paper on Fellowships, Budget Request Information, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) -- Bangkok Office -- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SSEA -- Educational Consultants for the Southeast Asia Program -- Memoranda, FAP, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SSEA -- Harvard-Pakistan Planning Commission Study Committee Reports, 1962 March (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - SSEA -- India -- Economic Aid and Development -- Reports, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SSEA -- India -- Education -- Memoranda regarding Resource Base, Background, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - SSEA -- India -- Education Commission -- Members List and Bios, Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - SSEA -- India -- Ford Foundation Assistance -- John Bresnan Statement Before International Technical Cooperation and Assistance Panel, President's Science Advisory Council, 1966 September 23 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SSEA -- India -- Foreign Training Programming -- Memoranda regarding Potential Funding of PhD Study-Related Travel Costs, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SSEA -- India -- History of Foundation Activities Report (separated), 1966 February (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - SSEA -- India -- Inter-Uterine Devices -- Correspondence regarding Delivery and Distribution, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - SSEA -- India -- Travel and Study Awards -- List, Memoranda regarding Commitments, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- English Language Programs -- Report, Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- Reference File -- Correspondence regarding Coup and Aftermath, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- Ramparts Magazine Article regarding Berkeley Mafia and Indonesia Massacre and Ford Foundation Response, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - SSEA -- Karachi Office -- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - SSEA -- Karachi Office -- Correspondence regarding Litigation, etc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - SSEA -- Kuala Lumpur Office -- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - SSEA -- Kuala Lumpur Office -- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - SSEA -- Manila Office -- Correspondence regarding Bangkok Visit, Clipping, etc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Melvin Fox Subject Files, 1953-1967; II; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  These files document the Language Development Study project of the International Training and Research Program. The files contain a copy of the ITR report by Cleon Swayzee, with related memoranda and comment letters.
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program -- Swayzee, Cleon O. -- Comment Letters, Internal Memoranda (1 of 2), 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program -- Swayzee, Cleon O. -- Report (2 of 2), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Language Development -- Background Papers (1 of 2), circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Language Development -- Background Papers (2 of 2), circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Language Development -- Correspondence regarding Language Study, etc., 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Language Development -- Foreign or Second Language Activities Report, Conference Papers, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Herbert Passin Subject Files, 1957-1966; III; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  Mr. Passin's subject files primarily pertain to his work as a consultant and expert on Japan. Other files document the Foundation's grant-making activities in China, Korea or Tibet.
  - American Assembly -- U.S.-Japan -- Notes, Correspondence regarding Wada Zentaro, 1966 August-September (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Asian Conservation Laboratory, Inc. -- Fellowship Application, Reports, Background, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bereday Teachers College -- Japanese School -- Reports, Reference (Japanese), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chuo University -- Correspondence regarding Grant Request, Background, 1963 June-July (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ekvali, Robert B. -- Tibet -- Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - English as a Second Language -- Meeting Notes, Transcript, Background, 1966 March 30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Glueck, Sheldon -- Correspondence, Background, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program, 1965 December 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hong Kong -- Chinese University -- Memorandum regarding Ford Foundation Support, 1965 March 18-19 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hong Kong -- Grey, Robert -- Correspondence with Colonial Secretary G.T. Rowe, 1964 January (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Institute of International Relations -- Japan-Inoki -- Correspondence regarding Proposal, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International House Meeting -- Japan -- Memoranda regarding Ford Foundation Support, Wealth of Japan, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Japan Center for International Understanding -- Kosaka -- Memorandum, 1965 October 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Japan Parliamentary Exchange -- Memorandum, Correspondence, Background, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Japan Program -- Basic Dockets, Memoranda, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Japan Program -- Memoranda -- regarding Japan Trip, Philippines and Korea, Illustrative Projects (1 of 2), 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Japan Program -- Memoranda -- regarding IA activities, Japan projects, etc. (2 of 2), 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Japan Socialist Party -- Correspondence regarding Study, 1963 May-June (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Japan Society -- Japanese-American File -- Arts Program, 1965 June (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Japan Trip -- Itinerary, Priorities, Memorandum regarding Ford Foundation in Korea, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Kiyosato Educational Experiment -- Rusch, Paul -- Correspondence regarding Farm School, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Korea -- Memoranda, Notes, Background on Assistance to Taiwan and Korea, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Kosaka -- Japan Council for International Understanding (JCIU) -- Correspondence regarding Trip, Organization, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Labor Movement in Japan -- Karsh, Bernard -- Memoranda, Background, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mancall of Harvard Translation Project regarding Japanese and American Scholarship on Communist China, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - McCray, Porter -- John D. Rockefeller 3rd Fund -- Correspondence regarding Arts in Japan, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation) Educational Television -- Correspondence regarding American Educational TV Exchange with Japan, 1963 March-September (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Passin, Herbert -- Japan Trip Notes, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Reischauer, Edwin (Ambassador) -- Correspondence regarding China, 1963 January-April (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Rose, Elizabeth -- Correspondence regarding Proposed United Nations University in Asia, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Russian Studies in Japan -- Robert Byrnes Report (separated), 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Rutgers University -- Correspondence regarding International Conference on Japanese-American Cultural Relations, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Seki, Yoshihiko -- Study Abroad Candidates, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Slater, Joseph E. -- Notes on Hong Kong Discussions on Proposed Chinese Federal University, etc., 1962 November (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Slater, Joseph E. -- Notes on Japan, 1962 October 25 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - St. Paul 's University -- Rikkyo -- Correspondence regarding Research on Postwar Japanese Economy, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stone-Passin Japan Trip -- Itinerary, Memoranda on Ford Foundation in Japan, Background, 1962 March (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stone, Shepard -- Travel and Study Awards, Items for Discussion, etc., 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tamagawa Gakuen University -- Correspondence, Background, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tobata Proposal regarding Japanese Modern Agriculture -- Memorandum regarding Applicability to Asia and Joint IA-ITR Funding, 1963 October 7 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Eisenstadt, Samuel -- Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- General Lists, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Procedures, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - TV Exchange -- Louis G. Cowan Summary and Recommendations regarding American Educational TV Exchange with Japan, 1964 February 5 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Von Briessen, Fritz -- Correspondence, 1963 March-April (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Washington, University of -- Modern China Project Proposal, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Yomiuri -- World Conference on Peace, Tokyo and Kyoto, Japan -- Correspondence, Background, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 15)